<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>CMC - Mailchimp® for Joomla™ - User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

      <surname>Dimitrov</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>compojoom.com</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>31.07.2012</pubdate>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "The GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book covers the use of the CMC - <ulink
      url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">Mailchimp</ulink>®
      for Joomla™ extension. It does not cover any other extension available
      on compojoom.com .</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <article>
    <para><revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>CMC - 1.0.0 - Revision 0.1</revnumber>

          <date>31.07.2012</date>

          <author>
            <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

            <surname>Dimitrov</surname>
          </author>

          <revremark>1st Draft</revremark>
        </revision>
      </revhistory><revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>CMC - 1.4.0 - Revision 0.2</revnumber>

          <date>21.09.2013</date>

          <author>
            <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

            <surname>Dimitrov</surname>
          </author>

          <revremark>1st Draft</revremark>
        </revision>
      </revhistory></para>
  </article>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introducing CMC</title>

      <para>CMC is a Joomla extension that integrates with the <ulink
      url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">Mailchimp</ulink>
      API. Its functionality includes, but is not limited to displaying your
      Mailchimp lists and users directly in your Joomla backend. It comes with
      a Joomla module that will let you easily create newsletter subscription
      forms on your site.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Indicative uses</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Newsletter subscription. CMC makes it really easy to publish
            your Mailchimp subscription form on a Joomla based website and
            doesn't require you to create or copy/paste any HTML code.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Access information about your Mailchimp lists and users
            right in your Joomla backend</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation and updates</title>

    <para>Installing CMC is no different than installing any other Joomla!™
    extension on your site. You can read the complete instructions for
    installing Joomla!™ extensions on the <ulink
    url="http://help.joomla.org/content/view/1476/235/">official help
    page</ulink> .Throughout this chapter we assume that you are familiar with
    these instructions and we will not duplicate them.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Getting the installation packages</title>

      <para>You can download the latest installation packages by visiting our
      site at <ulink
      url="https://compojoom.com">https://compojoom.com</ulink>. Go to
      Download -&gt; CMC menu item. The releases are listed in descending
      order with the newest release always on top. Click on the release number
      and then download the ZIP package.</para>

      <para>The installation package can be installed on Joomla 2.5 &amp; 3.x.
      You can use the installation package to update from previous version as
      well; just install it, without uninstalling the old package.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Updating to the latest version</title>

      <section>
        <title>Checking for the latest version and upgrading</title>

        <para>The easiest way to check for a new version of CMC is to navigate
        to your Joomla backend -&gt; Extensions -&gt; Extension manager -&gt;
        Update. Click on find updates. If we've issues a CMC update that is
        compatible with your Joomla version it show up in the list.</para>

        <para>Another way to check for the latest updates is to visit our site
        https://compojoom.com and go to Downloads-&gt;CMC. The latest
        available version is going to be on the top.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the CMC component</title>

    <para>Congrats! It seems that you have the first step - the installation
    behind you! Now let us quickly sum up what you need to do after the
    installation. Go to the extensions dashboard -&gt; click on Options in the
    top right -&gt; provide your <ulink
    url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">Mailchimp</ulink>
    API key and enter a webhooks key. Copy the webhooks URL to your lists
    settings on Mailchimp! Now the component is all setup and you can run your
    first synchronisation (go to the list view). Once you've run the
    synchronisation and if everything went fine you can go ahead and publish
    the subscription module and let users subscribe.</para>

    <para>This was the absolute minimum of what you need to do. If you are an
    advanced user the steps most probably didn't scare you. If on the other
    hand you didn't understand what to do let us look at each step in
    details.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Dashboard</title>

      <para>The dashboard provides you with a quick access to each view of the
      component. You also have a newsfeed module on the right that will
      display the latest information about the component taken right out of
      our blog.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/dashboard.PNG"/>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Options</title>

      <para>From the top right of your dashboard you can access the component
      Options.</para>

      <para><graphic fileref="images/options.PNG"/>The options are divided
      into 2 tabs - "Main Settings" &amp; "Permissions" . The main settings is
      the area where you need to provide your API keys (we'll discuss that in
      a second) . Permissions is the place where you would define who is able
      to access the component in the backend. We use the standard Joomla ACL
      for that so it is best that you read the documentation available at
      <ulink
      url="http://docs.joomla.org/Access_Control_List/1.6-2.5/Tutorial">http://docs.joomla.org</ulink>
      .</para>

      <section>
        <title>Mailchimp API key</title>

        <para>In order for the component to work you will need to provide your
        Mailchimp API key. To get the key log into your profile on
        mailchimp.com . Then on the left click on your name -&gt; Account
        Settings -&gt; Extras -&gt; API keys -&gt; API keys.</para>

        <graphic fileref="images/mailchimp_api_key.png"/>

        <para>You will be presented with a list a keys similar to this
        one</para>

        <graphic fileref="images/mailchimp_api_keys.PNG"/>

        <para>Select the Mailchimp key (or if it doesn't exist create one!),
        copy it and then paste it in the Mailchimp API key in the CMC
        configuration settings.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Webhooks URL</title>

        <para>Webhooks are a way for <ulink
        url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">Mailchimp</ulink>
        to send information related to your lists and users to your site.
        Webhooks allows CMC to offer a 2 way synchronisation of lists. In
        simple English this means that - whenever a user unsubscribes on
        Mailchimp - this will be reflected in the backend of your website.
        Whenever you modify an user on mailchimp.com -&gt; the modified
        information will be also show in your backend.</para>

        <para>In order for the webhooks support to work you need to provide
        the URL to your site in the Mailchimp list settings. Since this URL is
        publicly available it means that everyone would be able to send data
        to your site. To prevent this we automatically generate a secret key
        for your site and append it to the url. The key is like a password
        -&gt; if someone tries to call your webhooks URL without the key -&gt;
        the system will just do nothing. On the other side - if the request to
        that URL has the correct webhooks key, then the system will proceed
        with the processing of the request.</para>

        <para>So, long story short - copy the URL from the webhooks URL field
        and give it to mailchimp:</para>

        <important>
          <para>Don't forget to save the settings! If you don't do so the key
          generated for the webhook URL won't be saved and mailchimp won't be
          able to properly authenticate on your site!</para>
        </important>

        <graphic fileref="images/lists.PNG"/>

        <para>Once you've reached the list view at the top you'll see a bar
        with settings related to your list. Click on "Settings" -&gt;
        "Webhooks" as shown in the screen shot below</para>

        <graphic fileref="images/webhooks-select.png"/>

        <para>Now you should be presented with a screen similar to this
        one:</para>

        <graphic fileref="images/webhooks-add.PNG"/>

        <para>Provide the copied URL in the "Callback URL" section and click
        on "Add Webhook". If your website is reachable through the web (not an
        intranet or localhost) you should see a message that everything went
        fine.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Lists</title>

      <para>On the list view you'll see the lists that you have currently
      synced up with <ulink
      url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">Mailchimp</ulink>.
      If this is a new installation you'll have to sync the lists that you
      want to manage on this site. Just click on the Sync button and follow
      the steps on the screen.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Users</title>

      <para>The user screen allows you to see all the users subscribed to all
      of your lists.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/users.PNG"/>

      <para>By clicking on the email of an user you will be presented with a
      view that has more information about him. Similar to this one:</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/user.PNG"/>

      <para>You can modify the user email, names and status. You are also
      presented with the Mailchimp group and interest fields in raw form. (in
      a future version we plan to add support for editing them as well)</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Plugins</title>

      <para/>

      <section>
        <title>Ecommerce360 tracking</title>

        <para>Mailchimp's Ecommerce360 tracking is designed to help you
        measure the ROI of your email campaigns. Now to make use of this
        feature in Joomla all you need to do is to activate one of the plugins
        for the supported shopping carts/subscription extensions. We currently
        support</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="https://www.akeebabackup.com/products/akeeba-subscriptions.html">Akeebasubs</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.hikashop.com/">Hika</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="https://compojoom.com/joomla-extensions/matukio-events-management-made-easy">Matukio</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://www.jpayplans.com/">Payplans</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://redcomponent.com/redcomponent/redshop">Redshop</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://virtuemart.net/">Virtuemart</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section>
          <title>Enabling Ecommerce360 tracking</title>

          <para>First when you are sending a new campaign in Mailchimp enable
          the ecommerce tracking feature there. This will ensure that the
          links in your email contain the necessary tracking
          information.</para>

          <para>Then login into the backend of your Joomla website and go to
          Extensions -&gt; Plugin Manager. Enable the "CMC - Ecom360" plugin
          and one of the available plugins for your shopping cart/subscription
          system ( see the previous section on information about currently
          supported systems).</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Developing your own ecommerce360 tracking plugin</title>

          <para>Developing a plugin for your own shopping cart is very easy.
          Prerequisites are that you know PHP.</para>

          <para>The easiest way to understand the ecommerce360 plugins would
          be to look at the already existing plugins in plugins/system/ (all
          ecommerce360 plugins start with ecom360 in their name). You'll
          notice that in each plugin we have the following line:</para>

          <programlisting>JLoader::discover('CmcHelper', JPATH_ADMINISTRATOR . '/components/com_cmc/helpers/');</programlisting>

          <para>With it we are including all available CMC Helpers. This
          ensures that you can call the
          CmcHelperEcom360::sendOrderInformations function and pass to it all
          the necessary parameters with your order information.</para>

          <programlisting>public static function sendOrderInformations(
		$store_id,
		$store_name = "Store name",
		$order_id = 0,
		$total_amount = 0,
    	$tax_amount = 0,
		$shipping_amount = 0,
        $products = array(
						0 =&gt; array(
							"product_id" =&gt; 0,
							"sku" =&gt; "",
							"product_name" =&gt; "",
							"category_id" =&gt; 0,
							"category_name" =&gt; "",
							"qty" =&gt; 1.00,
							"cost" =&gt; 0.00
						)
					)
	)</programlisting>

          <para>$store_id = unique id for the store sending the order (20
          bytes max)</para>

          <para>$store_name = a "nice" name for the store - typically the base
          web address (ie, "store.mailchimp.com")</para>

          <para>$order_id = the Order id</para>

          <para>$total_amount = The Order Total</para>

          <para>$tax_amount = the total tax paid</para>

          <para>$shipping_amount = the total paid for Shipping Fees</para>

          <para>$products = an array containing the individual products(items)
          for each order.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Registration plugins</title>

        <para/>

        <section>
          <title>User - CMC Registration plugin</title>

          <para>If you want to subscribe your users to your newsletter during
          the registration process on your site and if you use the standard
          joomla registration, then you can use this plugin to show a
          newsletter checkbox. Not only this, but you have the option to
          select any field from your subscription form (that you've created on
          mailchimp.com). In the basic settings select the list that you want
          your users to be subscribed to, configure which fields should be
          shown during the registration process &amp; just enable the plugin
          after that. That is all you have to do. Now when you navigate to
          your registration page you should see a "newsletter checkbox", once
          selected the configured fields should show up.</para>

          <important>
            <para>Please note that any required field that you've created on
            mailchimp.com needs to be selected in the plugin settings. If you
            don't do this, then users won't be able to subscribe to your
            newsletter as the required fields won't be shown during the
            registration process.</para>

            <para>There is an exception to this - if you use the field
            mapping. You most probably don't want to ask the user for his
            email, first name and last name - as he already entered those in
            registration form. If you enter the above code in the field
            mapping, then we will read the email, fname and last name out of
            the information that the user has provided in the form. This makes
            the subscription process easier as the users don't have to enter
            the same information twice. </para>

            <programlisting>EMAIL=email
FNAME=name:0
LNAME=name:1</programlisting>
          </important>

          <note>
            <para>If new user account activation is turned off and your users
            are immediatly registered on your site, then we will also register
            them for the newsletter, but they will have first to confirm this
            by clicking the "subscribe me" button in the email that they will
            receive from Mailchimp.</para>

            <para>If new user account activation is set to self (which means
            that they will receive an activation email), then we will activate
            their subscription without sending them a second mail. Whenever
            they click the activation link they will be subscribed to your
            newsletter as well.</para>

            <para>In both cases this makes sure that we follow the double
            opt-in process.</para>
          </note>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Community - CMC Registration plugin (Jomsocial
          plugin)</title>

          <para>If you use Jomsocial and you want to subscribe your users to
          your newsletter during the registration on your site you'll need to
          activate and configure this plugin.</para>

          <important>
            <para>Make sure that the User - CMC Registration plugin is turned
            on! Otherwise this plugin won't function properly &amp; your users
            won't be subscribed to the newsletter when they click the
            activation link in the confirmation email.</para>
          </important>

          <important>
            <para>Read the chapter on "User - CMC Registration plugin"! The
            fields that are required in mailchimp have to be present in the
            newsletter form, unless you've configured a field mapping. The
            standard field mapping for email, first name and last name looks
            like this:</para>

            <programlisting>EMAIL=jsemail
FNAME=jsname:0
LNAME=jsname:1</programlisting>
          </important>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Community Builder plugin</title>

          <para>The Community Builder (CB) plugin allows you to show a
          newsletter checkbox during the registration process on your site if
          you use CB for registrations. This plugin will show a checkbox and
          all the fields that you want your users to fill up in order to be
          subscribed for your newsletter. To enable the plugin navigate to
          your joomla backend -&gt; components -&gt; community builder -&gt;
          plugin Manager -&gt; CMC - Newsletter registration</para>

          <important>
            <para>This plugin is automatically installed with CMC if we detect
            CB during the installation. If you have installed CMC first and
            after that CB, then you'll have to install CMC again in order for
            the plugin to be installed. You don't need to uninstall first -
            you can just install the same version over the old one.</para>
          </important>

          <important>
            <para>The fields that are required in mailchimp have to be present
            in the newsletter form, unless you've configured a field mapping.
            The standard field mapping for email, first name and last name
            looks like this:</para>

            <programlisting>EMAIL=email
FNAME=name:0
LNAME=name:1</programlisting>
          </important>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the CMC Module</title>

    <para>When you install the CMC component, we also install a frontend
    module that you can use to display a newsletter subscription form on your
    site. Go to Extensions -&gt; Module Manager and in the list find the CMC -
    Newsletter subscription module.</para>

    <para><note>
        <para>If you don't find the module in the list click on New and then
        select the CMC - Newsletter subscription module</para>
      </note>The basic parameters of the module should look something similar
    to this:</para>

    <graphic fileref="images/mod_cmc_basic_options.PNG"/>

    <note>
      <para>You are already asking - what is the field "field mapping" for?
      Your newsletter form generally requests information from the user that
      you could possibly have. For example for logged in users you have their
      email and name. So why should you ask your login users to type all this?
      You could prefill the form with their e-mail and name and just ask them
      to hit the submit button. This is where the field mapping comes in
      handy. There is no way for us to guess which field in mailchimp
      corresponds to the user object in Joomla. That is why we need you to
      provide this information manually. For example here is a standard
      configuration that would fill out the email, first name and last
      name:</para>

      <programlisting>EMAIL=email
FNAME=name:0
LNAME=name:1</programlisting>

      <para>On the left you have the field tag as specified in Mailchimp. On
      the right you have the corresponding Joomla user property. Maybe you are
      already asking yourself - what is the 0 and the 1 after the name? Well,
      in Joomla the first name and last name are stored in the same database
      field. We take the value in this field, we create an array out of it. 0
      is basically the first value in the array, the 1 the second. So in our
      case 0 is the first name and 1 the second name. </para>
    </note>

    <para>You need to select a list from the drop down field. Once you do this
    the page will refresh and you'll be presented with the fields and interest
    groups options for your list.</para>

    <graphic fileref="images/mod_cmc_group_options.PNG"/>

    <para>Select the fields you want to show in the frontend and click on save
    once ready.</para>

    <para><important>
        <para>Please make sure to select all the fields that you've marked as
        required in Mailchimp. Failure to do so will result in not working
        subscriptions as <ulink
        url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">Mailchimp</ulink>
        will refuse to subscribe the users to the list, because some fields
        are missing.</para>
      </important>Depending on the fields and interest groups that you've
    selected the module will display different options in the frontend. Here
    is a screen shot of a module that has only the Email, First and Last name
    fields selected</para>

    <graphic fileref="images/mod_cmc_frontend.PNG"/>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Tips &amp; tricks</title>

    <para/>

    <section>
      <title>Styling the CMC module</title>

      <para>The module comes with 2 css files: cmc.css &amp;
      bootstrap-form.css both located in media/mod_cmc/css . In the settings
      of the module you have the option to turn off the bootstrap-form.css
      file. You don't need it if your template is using the bootstrap
      framework. </para>

      <para>If you are not happy with the way the module look you'll have to
      style it :) Unfortunatly we can't give you any tips here. Except maybe
      if you don't know how you <ulink
      url="https://compojoom.com/blog/entry/how-to-use-firebug-to-change-the-css-of-a-joomla-extension">should
      learn to use firebug for css editing</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Where to go from here?</title>

    <para>If you encounter any problems or have any suggestions don't hesitate
    to contact us. We provide top-notch <ulink
    url="https://compojoom.com/forum/cmc-mailchimp-for-joomla">forum
    support</ulink>. Just drop us a line!</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
